Guide to the Jack Friel University History Collection 1850-1978 (Bulk 1976-1977) MS 004 MS 004
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Jack Friel University History Collection
Bulk, 1976-1977
1850-1978, (Bulk 1976-1977)
MS 004
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
3.0 Linear feet
The Jack Friel University History Collection is his work in gathering information about the history of this university. Starting in 1976, under a grant authorized by the WestConn Foundation, Friel began to collect information about the history of then named Western Connecticut State College with the intended goal of writing the history of the college. Friel, who was a former graduate student, took on the task with the help of two students, Ronald Douglas and Sandy Connor. When it became apparent that he would be unable to accomplish his goal, he agreed to leave all the information he had collected with the school so the story could be told at later time.
Friel, John V.
Provenance
Donated by Jack Friel.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
For nearly twenty-six years, John V. Friel lived in Aruba working for Exxon Oil Company. In 1968, Friel and his wife moved to Newtown, Connecticut. Having spent most of his life in business, he decided he wanted a change and went back to school. It was his eventual goal to go to law school, preferably at either Yale or UConn. He finished his undergraduate work at Scared Heart University before enrolling in the graduate program at WestConn. He received his MA in history in May 1976, but would remain at the college working as a graduate assistant. It was during this time that he began his research on the history of the college. While he was unable to complete the goal of writing the history on the college, his research efforts, as well as his assistants, are evident in this collection.
The Jack Friel University History Collection is his work in gathering information about the history of this university. Starting in 1976, under a grant authorized by the WestConn Foundation, Friel began to collect information about the history of then named Western Connecticut State College with the intended goal of writing the history of the college. Friel, who was a former graduate student, took on the task with the help of two students, Ronald Douglas and Sandy Connor. When it became apparent that he would be unable to accomplish his goal, he agreed to leave all the information he had collected with the school so the story could be told at later time.
Scope and Content Note
The collection spans from 1850-1978 with the bulk ranging from 1976-1977.
While this collection is relatively small, the materials within the collection detail a great amount of information about the history of the university. It chronicles the transition of the school from the establishment of the Danbury Normal School in 1903 all the way to its status as Western Connecticut State College in 1977.
The collection is comprised of Friel's notes, plans, outline, and rough draft. It also contains school catalogs and brochures, letters, memoirs, yearbook excerpts, program descriptions, Board of Education reports, lists of activities, audiotape interviews and newspaper clippings.
The heart of the collection is the oral history interviews. Several notable individuals were interviewed for this project including Ruth Haas, Truman Warner, Gertrude Braun, Burton Cook, and Charlotte Isham among others. Cassette tapes have an accepted shelf life of anywhere from 10-30 years before the content is lost. Jack Friel’s interview audiocassettes were recorded in the winter of 1976-77 and therefore were in jeopardy of being lost. In 2009, these recordings were digitized and links to those recordings are listed in the inventory. None of the tapes were edited or excluded from this process. These specific interviews mentioned below serve to highlight the larger purpose of digitizing all such material, so that they can be made readily available for all who wish to use them, and in a longer-lasting format. Generally, Friel was interested in how people remembered WCSU, the physical and academic development of WCSU, and WCSU’s relationship with Danbury and Connecticut. His interview style is conversational and sometimes a bit anecdotal. On a couple occasions, the recordings show signs of signal loss, speed variations, and noise. Generally, he conducted a formal interview but there are instances where the subject reads or records their own narrative. The tapes include interviews with former students: Mrs. Sheila Shearon(tape#34), Dr. Kathleen McGrory(tapes #16,17), and Mrs. Llewlyn Warner(tapes#21,22). These give unique insight into what it meant to attend WCSU, and what a degree from the institution afforded them. These interviews also contain rich descriptions of the daily routine of a WCSU student during the first half of the twentieth century. Interviews with Mr. Bill Ratchford (tape#07), Mr. Francis Collins (tape#04), and Mr. T. Clark Hull (tape#08), all of whom served in the state government, elucidate the struggle of obtaining funding for WCSU, specifically the development of the Westside campus that has as of January 2010 is still under construction. Aside from the numerous interviews in which Dr. Ruth A. Haas is discussed, there is also an interview with her (tape #01). One important thread running through the interviews is a discussion of Haas’ accomplishments, and her challenges as woman administrator. In many of the accounts, she is shown to be integral in the changing of WCSU from a predominately female teaching college to a full-fledged university with graduate programs.
Also of interest to researchers is a letter that was written to Friel by Margaret Perkins Camp, the daughter of the first principal of the Danbury Normal School, John Perkins. In it she recalls moving to Danbury from New Britain, growing up in the Danbury Normal School, and the teachers of the school including Dr. Lothrop Higgins.
The collection also contains information on the history of the Student Government Association and the Alumni Association. There is also information on other student and school activities. Friel also collected information on various different curriculum programs that were instituted at various points in the school's history. The collection contains information on both the "Nature of Man," and "Monuments of Culture," programs.
The collection also contains several copies of the school's catalogs that span several decades. It also contains copies of catalogs from the other three normal schools, which included New Britain, New Haven, and Willimantic.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged topically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Inventory
Related Material
Truman Warner Papers
Digitized audio interviews conducted by Friel in 1976-1977 are available at:
http://archives.library.wcsu.edu/collections/MS004
Danbury Normal School.; Danbury State Teachers College.; Western Connecticut State College.; Western Connecticut State University -- History.; Audiotapes.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Danbury (Conn.); Fliers (printed matter); Oral histories (document genres).; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Yearbooks.
- Inventory
  - Note cards Friel used to keep track of his research, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plan and rough draft, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    - plan: outlines Friel's research plans, 1977
    - rough draft: goes up to chapter four and has been edited, 1977
  - Bibliography and background, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Friel's uncompleted research donated to Ruth A. Haas Library archives, 1977
    - annotation (breakdown of materials), 1977
    - background on normal schools: Wilson, Lynn Winfield, "History of Fairfield County, Connecticut, 1639-1928," 1929; "Brief History of the New Haven Normal School," 1935
    - Nelson, Mrs. Haviland, "Henry Bernard, 1811-1900," circa 1900, Shumway, Gary L. and Williams G. Hartley, An Oral History Primer, 1973; Northrop, B.G., "High Schools," 1880; Knight, Edgar W., "Education in the United States," circa 1900; notes of William Conley on Sacred Heart University, 1974; "Teachers," 1967 (encyclopedia reference)
  - Memoirs, 1938-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - letter to Friel from Margaret Perkins Camp, December 15, 1976 (w/ summary of letter)
    - notes about the Danbury Normal School, "The 'New' Danbury Normal School circa 1903"
    - letter from William Georgen, M.D. class of 1917, "Memories and Vagaries, Wanderings and Meanderings Kindergarten, 1916-1917, in the Old Main"
    - letter from Gertrude Murphy, class of 1912
    - Greene, May A., "Danbury Teachers College: A Brief History," 1950
    - Danbury Teachers' College in Transition, 1938
  - Catalogs, 1904-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Catalogs 1904-1976: Supplement to Sandy Connor Report, 1976
    - Catalogs 1904-1976, 1976
    - Historical Highlights, (nd)
    - Connecticut School Document: State Normal-Training School, Danbury, 1904
    - Connecticut School Document: Correspondence Courses, 1906
    - DNS catalogs, "Catalogue: State Normal-Training School Danbury, Connecticut," (1904-1905; 1905-1906; 1908-1909; 1909-1910; 1910-1911; 1911-1912; 1913-1914; 1916-1917)
    - DNS catalogs, "Annual Catalog," (1920-1935)
  - School Brochures and Special Catalogs, 1960-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Why Build It Now, 1974
    - Memorial Hall: The College Union, circa 1960
    - Your Introduction to Danbury State College, circa 1961
    - Announcing a New M.A. in History, 1972
    - 1970-1971 Western Connecticut State College Women's Athletic Association, 1971
    - Study in Africa Summer 1973, 1973
    - Western Connecticut State College; Special Summer Secession at Ocean Park, Maine, 1973
    - Western Connecticut State College: Historical Development, 1974
    - Western Connecticut State College Summer Sessions, 1971; 1976
    - Western Connecticut State College, circa 1971
    - New Campus Chronology, September 17, 1976
  - Ronald Douglas Research Paper, "A Profile of Students Entering Danbury Normal School in Early Years", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yearbook excerpts, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student Activities, 1926-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - SGA minutes, 1926-1944
    - History of the SGA from 1950-1975
    - College Publications, April 29, 1976
    - College Publications: Conatus, 1976
    - Sampling of Student Handbooks, 1977
    - Major Traditions Summarized, 1975
    - Observations of Student Organizations as Seen Through a Study of the School Yearbook, 1976
    - Chronology of Historical Events at Western Connecticut State College, 1976
  - Alumni Association, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Alumni Association: Brief History, circa 1968
    - Danbury State Teachers College Alumni Association, 1941-42, 1941
    - Alumni News, 1956 (pgs. 8-10)
  - Program Descriptions, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Re-evaluation Report to the New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Danbury State College, November 4-6, 1963
    - Burke, Harold R., Dean of Student Affairs, "Observations on Growing Pains at WCSC," 1969
    - Greewald, Dr. H. Jonathan, "The Nature of Man Program: Danbury State College," circa 1966
    - The Nature of Man Sequence: An Interdisciplinary Program in Humanistic Studies, circa 1971
    - Monuments of Culture, Humanities course, Fall 1958
    - Monuments of Culture: The Communist Manifesto, Humanities course, Spring 1959
    - letter from Dr. Ruth A. Haas about Interim Program at Danbury Teachers College
    - Geographical List of Interim Projects
  - School, Miscellaneous, 1935-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Dober Report, 1967 (excerpts)
    - Enrollment Data from School Catalogs
    - student paper on legislative battle in 1903 to establish Danbury Normal School, circa 1970
    - Tufts, John (Dr.), "Chapter I: Environment of the Project," 1956
    - Maps and charts, 1977
    - Copies of Dr. Charlotte Isham's diploma (June 19, 1935)
    - Copy of Dr. Isham's teacher's contract
    - Letter from Raymond J. Trimpert (director) and Ronnie Kuroski (press secretary) of the Office of Student Affairs, October 7, 1977
    - Attendance Registers, (3 pgs.)
    - Ralph Jenkins obituary from The Inkling, October 1946
    - Chart, "Administrative Organization of Danbury State College," circa 1961
    - Chronology on history of the four Normal Schools (now the CSU system)
    - Statistics
    - Western Connecticut State College: Wescon Summer News, vol. I, no. 3, July 17, 1967
    - Enrollment of students by class and major, fall 1977
    - Historical Highlights, 1971; 1976
    - Statement of Purpose, circa 1977
    - various copies of school items used by President Bersi to secure money for Westside campus
  - State Board of Education, 1904-1976 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - Aide-Memoire, November 23, 1976
    - Present and Projected Student Enrollment, June 3, 1966
    - Legislation/ Board of Education Regulations- All Normal schools, circa 1965
    - Requirements for Admission to Connecticut State Normal Schools, September 1923
    - An Act Establishing the Teachers' College of Connecticut, 1933
    - An Act Changing the Name of Danbury State College, 1965
    - An Act Establishing a State System of Higher Education, 1965
    - Rules and Regulations Concerning the Granting of Degrees by the State Board of Education, 1934
    - Subjects of Interest from Biennial Report of the Board of Education, circa 1965
    - various reports on CT Normal Schools
    - State Examinations, 1904
    - Report of the Secretary, (from Conn. Public Documents), 1905; 1908; 1910; 1912; 1916; 1918; 1920-1923; 1925; 1928; 1930-1937; 1942; 1945; 1947
    - CT Public Documents, 1946-1965
    - College and University Enrollments, 1955-1957
  - Newspaper clippings, 1903-1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    -include clippings from Danbury News-Times, The Dee Tee Cee, and The Echo
  - Other Normal Schools, 1850-1904 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Catalogue: State Normal-Training School New Haven, Connecticut, 1904 (twelfth year)
    - Catalogue: State Normal-Training School Willimantic, Connecticut, 1904 (sixteenth year)
    - Catalogue: State Normal-Training School New Britain, Connecticut, 1904 (fifty third year)
    - Annual Report of the Trustees of the State Normal School, 1850
    - Hints to School Visitors: Respecting Applicants fro Admission to the State Normal School, circa 1850
    - First Annual Circular of the state Normal School at New Britain, 1851
    - Fourth Annual Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the State Normal School, New Britain, Conn., 1854
    - Catalogue of the Committee, Teachers and Pupils of the New Britain High School, 1854
  - Research, Miscellaneous, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - letters from Jack Friel to John W. Anderson (August 29, 1976), Ruth A. Haas (September 8, 1976), Ralph W. Carrington (December 9, 1976)
    - letters from Dr. Herbert Janick (August 2, 1976), John Anderson (September 2, 1976), Margaret Camp (September 21; 24; 27, 1976), Dr. Theodore Shannon (October 25, 1976), Mrs. Robert Shearon (December 2, 1976), Eleanor V. Geel (January 5, 1977)
    - Staff Bulletin, October 15, 1976
    - Announcement for Alumni Bulletin, (nd)
    - Suggested Story for Echo on Wescon History, (nd)
    - Pending Research for WesCon History, November 18, 1976
    - CLIO, "Western Connecticut State College Archives," May 1976
    - Items of Interest, etc., circa 1977
    - Research Projects, circa 1977
    - Institutions/ Persons Visited, 1977
    - Wescon History Project Sources, 1977
  - Arconti, Gino, parts 1 - 2 (tape #11, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 1)
    audiotape
  - Braun, Dr. Gertrude, parts 1 - 2 (tape #19, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Brunell, Dr. Gloria, (tape #18, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Collins, Francis, (tape #4, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Cook, Dr. Burton, parts 1 - 2 (tape #32, sides A/B) & parts 3 - 4 (tape #33, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Deegan, John, (tape #16, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Donnelly, Dr. Alice part 1 (tape #3, side B) & part 2 (tape #7, side B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Dyer, Jim, parts 1 - 2 (tape #8, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Esposito, Dr. William, part 1 (tape #4, side B) & part 2 (tape #10, side B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Friel, Sister Mary, (tape #18, side B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 10)
  - Fusco, Sharon, parts 1 - 2 (tape #30, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #31, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Goergen, Dr. William, part 1 (tape #26, side B) & part 2 (tape #28, side B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 12)
  - Greewald, Dr. Jonathan parts 1 - 2 (tape #29, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 13)
  - Groff, Dr. Donald, parts 1 - 2 (tape #24, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 14)
  - Haas, Dr. Ruth A, parts 1 - 2 (tape #1, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 15)
  - Hull, T. Clark, parts 1 - 2 (tape #6, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 16)
  - Isham, Dr. Charlotte, part 1 (tape #22, side B) & parts 2 - 3 (tape #23, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 17)
  - Kohl, Dr. Ruth, (tape #17, side B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 18)
  - McGrory, Dr. Kathleen, part 1 (tape #16, side B) & part 2 (tape #17, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 19)
  - McKee, Bill, parts 1 - 2 (tape #12, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 20)
  - Murphy, Gertrude, parts 1 - 2 (tape #9, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #10, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 21)
  - O'Connell, Corrinne, parts 1 - 2 (tape #27, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #28, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 22)
  - Ratchford, Bill, (tape #7, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 23)
  - Rudner, Dr. M.J., (tape #13, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 24)
  - Shearon, Sheila, (tape #34, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 25)
  - Tufts, Dr. John, parts 1 - 2 (tape #25, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #26, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 26)
  - Vacha, Dr. Kathryn, part 1 (tape #13, side B) & parts 2 - 3 (tape #14, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 27)
  - Wagner, Neil, parts 1 - 2 (tape #5, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 28)
  - Warner, Mrs. Llewlyn, parts 1 - 2 (tape #21, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #22, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 29)
  - Warner, Dr. Truman, parts 1 - 2 (tape #2, sides A/B) & part 3 (tape #3, side A), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 30)
  - Whitcomb, Dr. Mervin, parts 1 - 2 (tape #20, sides A/B), 1976-1977 (Box 3, Item 31)